<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An elegie on the famous and renowned lady, for eloquence and wit, Madam Mary Carlton, otherwise styled, the German Princess.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.3[20]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885175</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885175</idno>
            <idno type="VID">182505</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03230)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 182505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A4:1[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An elegie on the famous and renowned lady, for eloquence and wit, Madam Mary Carlton, otherwise styled, the German Princess.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Speed,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Oh dire misfortune! 'twas a cruel fate ..."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Carleton, Mary, 1642?-1673 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Elegiac poetry, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:182505:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <head>AN ELEGIE On the Famous and Renowned LADY, for Eloquence and Wit, Madam MARY CARLTON, Otherwiſe ſtyled, The German Princeſs.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OH Dire Misfortune! 'twas a cruel Fate</l>
               <l>Should make her wit the object of its hate.</l>
               <l>Death ſurely hath no mercy in his ſting,</l>
               <l>To nooſe a Princeſs in a Hempen String.</l>
               <l>Had he or manners, or a ſharpen'd Dart,</l>
               <l>He had e're now ſurpriz'd her Martial heart;</l>
               <l>And not admitted her in all the throng</l>
               <l>Of Beauties, to ride Conquereſs ſo long:</l>
               <l>But he in policy obſerv'd her will,</l>
               <l>Spar'd her to ſend more Griſts unto his Mill;</l>
               <l>For ſhe, whoſe Beauty lay within her pate,</l>
               <l>Slew more by Love, then Death could ſlay by hate.</l>
               <l>But yet we ſee in vain it is to groan,</l>
               <l>The Gallows, and the Grave, refuſeth none.</l>
               <l>Nor let the Reader now exalt his horn,</l>
               <l>None know their Doom ſo ſoon as they are born.</l>
               <l>And who is he that dares to have the skill</l>
               <l>To judge who next ſhall ride up <hi>Holborn-Hill?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor is it much material; Fate, we know,</l>
               <l>More ways then one unto the Grave can ſhow;</l>
               <l>Some by Beheading, ſome by a Surprize;</l>
               <l>Some by thoſe Darts ſhot from their Ladies Eyes:</l>
               <l>Nor has the Gallow-Tree been ill adorn'd,</l>
               <l>Lords, Knights and Gentlemen, have there bin ſcorn'd:</l>
               <l>'Tis not the manner of their Deaths that die,</l>
               <l>That make them odious, but their Obloquie.</l>
               <l>Detracting from good breeding, looks more black</l>
               <l>Then many faults, in them good breeding lack.</l>
               <l>The world miſcall'd her Cheat; when as her ſtrife</l>
               <l>Was to act Natures part, preſerve her life:</l>
               <l>Or if it was her Genius to approve</l>
               <l>O'th' Female Craft, its Sentiments of Love.</l>
               <l>Who can ill language on her Craft beſtow,</l>
               <l>In ſeeking to have two ſtrings to her Bow?</l>
               <l>Thus Fate with Ignominy doth reward</l>
               <l>Thoſe daring Souls, that ſeldom have regard</l>
               <l>To the ſucceſs of what they undertake,</l>
               <l>And turns a Golden Wedge into a Stake</l>
               <l>'Twas <hi>Canterbury,</hi> that thrice-happy Earth,</l>
               <l>Grew proud, becauſe it chanc't to give her birth.</l>
               <l>Her Father, though but mean by Pedigree,</l>
               <l>Liv'd well belov'd in that moſt ſpacious See;</l>
               <l>And ſhe grown up to years, acquiring man,</l>
               <l>Improv'd, till ſhe was Metropolitan:</l>
               <l>Yet her croſs ſtars too ſuddenly have hurld</l>
               <l>Her parts from hence, into another World.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>HER EPITAPH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>HEre lieth one was hurried hence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To make the World a recompence</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For Actions wrought by Wit and Luſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſe Cloſet now is in the Duſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then let her ſleep, for ſhe has Wit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will give Diſturbers Hit for Hit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Speed,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
